For this project you will need to have
このプロジェクトを進めるためには
downloaded the Stealth project files.
Stealth プロジェクトのファイルをダウンロードしておく必要があります。
You can download them from the downloads area
これはチュートリアルのダウンロードエリアから
of the tutorials site. The first thing we'll
取得できます。最初にやるべきことは新しいシーンを
do is make a new scene. Go to
作成することです。メニューから
File - New Scene, then go to
Fileをクリックして New Sceneを選択します。次に
File - Save Scene As
File -> Save Scene as を選んで
and save it in to the Scenes folder
Scenesフォルダに保存するようにして
and call it Stealth, with a capital S.
このときに名前変更を行い大文字を正しくStealthとします。
Now we need to drag the level geometry into
次にレベル上のオブジェクトを
the hierarchy so that it appears
Hierarchyビュー上に展開して
in the scene. In the Models folder locate
シーン上に表示されるようにします。Models フォルダにおいて
the model called env.. (short for 'environment')
env_stealth_static と名づけられた（env は environment の略）
.. _stealth_static.
モデルをみつけて下さい。
It looks like this.
実際は次のように表示されています。
Drag and drop this into the hierarchy.
これをHierarchyビュー上にドラッグ＆ドロップします。
It should be positioned at (0, 0, 0),
ポジションは(0, 0, 0)と
the origin of the 3D world.
3D 座標空間の原点になっているはずです。
But if it's not, click the cog on the right
もしなっていない場合は右端の歯車アイコンを右クリックをして
and choose reset.
Reset を選択します。
That's almost all of the geometry but there's
オブジェクトはほぼ全てこれでカバーできたのですが
one important part missing.
まだ重要なオブジェクトがまだひとつ残っています。
In the Models folder locate prop_battleBus.
Models フォルダにて prop_battleBusを見つけます。
It looks like this.
実際は次のように表示されています。
Drag and drop this into the hierarchy too.
これをHierarchyビュー上にドラッグ＆ドロップしますが
You'll notice that it's not in the right place.
正しい位置にはまだ配置できていません。
We need to place it into the parking bay
これはマップ中心の駐車位置に配置する
in the centre of the map.
必要があります。
Place it at position (-11, 0, 17.5)
場所を (-11, 0, 17.5) へ Place it at position (-11, 0, 17.5)
using the transform component in the Inspector.
インスペクタ上の Transform コンポーネントにて設定します。
Then rotate it by 270 degrees in the Y axis.
次に270度 Y軸まわりに回転をするよう入力します。
Your Battle Bus should now look like this.
これでBattle Busは次のように表示されます。
Next we need to add a collision mesh to the scene
次にシーン上にコリジョン メッシュを追加して、
to give it a physical presence.
物理的に衝突できるように設定します。
So highlight env_stealth_static in the hierarchy
このために env_stealth_static を Hierarchyビューで選択をして
and using the Add Component button
インスペクタ上でAdd Componentを
on the Inspector go to
クリックしたうえで
Physics and Mesh Collider.
Physicsの中のMesh Collider を選択します。
The mesh we want to use is a separate
複雑になりすぎないように、
simplified version of the scene
よりシンプルなシーンとしてあらかじめ用意された
called env_stealth_collision.
env_stealth_collision をこのときに選択して下さい。
When you select it, it should look like this.
選択すると、次のように表示されます。
Expand the FBX file to reveal the mesh underneath.
FBX ファイルを展開することで、隠れていたメッシュを表示して
Then with env_stealth_static selected
次にHierarchy上にあるenv_stealth_static
in the hierarchy, drag the mesh
Mesh をドラッグして
to the mesh property of the collider.
Collider の Meshプロパティ上にドロップします。
The next thing to deal with is lighting.
次に設定するのはライティングです。
We're going to use a mixture of baked and
ここでは焼き込みしたライトと動的なライトを組み合わせて
dynamic light. But before we get started
いくのですが、その前の準備として
we need to change some settings in the scene.
シーン上でいくつか設定変更が必要です。
We're going to start by making the environment
はじめに環境をstaticに設定することにします。
static. This tells Unity that this game object
こうすることで Unity はそのオブジェクトが移動しないものと判断して
won't move and can therefore be light mapped.
ライトマッピングを行うことが出来るようになります。
Highlight env_stealth_static and
env_stealth_staticおよび
prop_battleBus in the hierarchy
prop_battleBusをHierarchyビューで選択します。
and then click the Static checkbox in the
次にインスペクタの右上で static の
top right of the inspector. You'll then be
チェックボックスをクリックすると
asked whether you want child objects of
選択したオブジェクトの子オブジェクトもstaticとしたいか
what you've selected to be static.
聞かれるので
We do, so choose yes.
Yesを選択します。
The environment is made up of two parts
環境は2つの要素から構成されていて、
the play area
プレイするエリア（Play Area）と
and the extents.
周りの境界線（Extents）です。
We're going to set some layers for them
次にレイヤーを設定して
so that they can be effected by lights appropriately.
適切にライティングされるようにします。
Open the Environment hierarchy
env_stealth_static を Hierarchy ビューで選択して
and select every child object except
extents以外の子オブジェクトを全て
for the extents.
選択します。
Then also select the prop_battleBus.
さらにprop_battleBus も選択して、
We'll set these to the layer called
これらPlayAreaレイヤーに
PlayArea.
移動します。
And again you will be asked if you want to apply
今回もこのレイヤーを
this layer to the child objects, and we do
子オブジェクトにも適用するか再び聞かれるので
so choose yes.
これもYesを選択します。
Finally choose the extents
最後にextentsを選択して
and set it to the layer called Extents
Extentsレイヤーに移動します。
and choose yes when prompted.
今回も聞かれたときにYesを選択します。
For neatness and consistency we've established
整理整頓して一貫性を保つために
a naming convention in this project
このプロジェクトではネーミングルールを定めているので
and we're going to rename the camera as such.
カメラもそれに従うように名前変更をします。
Change the main camera game object's name
メインカメラのオブジェクト名を
to camera_main.
camera_mainに変更します。
We're also going to setup the camera to
さらにカメラのレンダリングを
render with deferred lighting.
Deferred Lightingにするために
Under the Rendering Path setting in the
Camera コンポーネント配下の
camera component
Rendering Path 設定において
choose Deferred Lighting.
Deferred Lighting を選択します。
We also want to change the camera's background
さらにカメラの背景色を黒に
colour to black. So under Background
変更します。Backgroundの横の
click on the colour block
カラー選択ボックスをクリックして、
and then drag down to black
下までスクロールして黒色を選択して、
and close the colour picker.
カラー選択ボックを閉じます。
Finally we want to make sure that the camera
最後にカメラが不必要な部分まで
is not trying to render too much
レンダリングしないように設定をしてきます。
so we'll change the far clipping plane
それでは Far Clipping Plane を
to 100 instead of 1000.
1000から100に変更します。
This also improves accuracy of rendering.
これによりレンダリング精度も向上します。
Now we are going to add lights to the scene.
次にシーンにライトを追加していきます。
The lighting for the scene is time consuming
シーンのライティングは作業時間がかかるため、
and so we have designed the majority of the
このレッスンとしてはあらかじめ
lighting and provided it for you as a prefab.
大部分をプレハブというテンプレートで用意しています。
Don't worry, you will learn how to light
ここでスキップしたライティングのやり方は
what we have left out later. Drag in the
後で学んでくので、心配する必要はありません。
lights_baked prefab from the prefabs folder.
Prefabs フォルダから Lights_baked プレハブをドラッグして
and drop it into the hierarchy panel.
Hierarchy パネル上にドロップします。
If it's not already, ensure that the
もし (0, 0, 0) となってなければ
position is (0, 0, 0).
このときに修正します。
Now when looking at our scene we can choose
これでシーンをみるときにライティングを有効化にするためは
to show the lighting by clicking on the
太陽の形のアイコンが
sun icon at the top of the scene view.
シーンビュー上部にあるので、クリックします。
And you should also be aware that if you
さらに 3D Gizmos が表示されていなければ
aren't using 3D gizmos then you can toggle
これらはトグルにより切り替えることが出来ます。
using the Gizmos drop down of the right-hand side
操作としては、Scene ビューの上部右端にある
of the top of the scene view,
3D Gizmos ドロップダウンを使用します。
and you can also scale the gizmos there.
さらにGizmosをここでスケールすることも出来ます。
Bare in mind that you'll also see controls
選択したときにもライトのコントロールは表示されるので
for the lights when selecting them.
覚えておくと便利です。
So if you don't want to see all these overlays
このため全てのオーバーレイを非表示にしたい場合は Hierarchy 上で
simply click off them in the hierarchy.
別のところをクリックして選択状態を外します。
You should also be aware that if the scene
もしUnity作業中にシーンのパフォーマンス低下が起きた場合
is performing badly whilst working in Unity
に覚えておくと便利なこととして
you can toggle Built-in Lighting off
ビルトインのライティングは無効に切り替える操作は
in the scene view to have it perform
同様にScene ビュー上で行うことが出来ます。
a lot more quickly.
これでパフォーマンスはずいぶんと向上します。
And then simply toggle it back on when you want
逆に設定を再び有効にすれば
to check your lighting.
ライティングの状況を確認できます。
To complete the lighting for the scene
このシーンのライティングを完成するには
we need to create some lights for the room
まだライティングされてない部屋のライトを
that's currently unlit. You'll find it in
作成する必要があり
the lower right corner of the map.
それらはマップの右下隅にあります。
It looks like this.
次のように表示されているものです。
Start by creating a Point light.
初めにポイントライトを作成します。
Click on the Create button on the hierarchy
Hierarchy ビューで Create ボタンをクリックして
and choose Point Light.
ポイントライトを選択します。
Using the translate tool position it within the room.
位置調整ツールで変更して部屋の中に配置します。
We'll start with the first of three somewhere like this.
初めに３つのうちひとつを次の場所に置きます。
To keep with our naming convention
ネーミングルールに準拠させるため、
we'll rename this point light
ポイントライトの名前変更をして
light_playArea_point.
light_playArea_pointとします。
Next we're going to adjust the colour
次にライトのカラーを黄色に
of the light to a yellow colour.
調整します。
This should feel more like a real light bulb
これにより白いライトと比べてより電球として
than white light.
リアリティが感じられます。
Click the colour block on the light component
Light コンポーネントのカラーを選択して
and then choose a yellow-ish light.
次に黄色のライトを選びます。
Something like that.
次のような色です。
Note the values that I have in R,G,B and A
今回、値として設定している R、G、B、A を控えておけば
whenever you're trying to copy a colour that
自身でチュートリアルと全く同じ色を再現することが
I have in a tutorial.
出来ます。
Now we'll reduce the range slightly.
次にレンジを少し縮小します。
Currently it looks a little bit intense,
現在はライト強度が強すぎるので
so we'll change that down to a value of 8.
値を 8 に変更します。
The last setting we need to change
最後に変更が必要な設定はライトマッピング設定です。
We need to make sure that this light is
このライトを焼き込みのみとする必要があり、
baked only. Otherwise it will be rendered as
そうしなければリアルタイムでレンダリングされ
real-time and effect performance.
パフォーマンス影響が出てしまいます。
Under Light Mapping change Auto to Baked Only.
Light Mapping の設定を Baked Only にします。
We're going to have two more lights in this room
この部屋にはあと二つだけライトを設定して
to make sure it's lit properly.
きちんとライティングされるようにします。
These lights are going to be the same
これらのライトは先ほど作成したものと
as the one we've just made so we'll
ほぼ同じです。
duplicate them and place them appropriately
これらは複製して適切に部屋に配置を行い、
in the room. Select the point light
このため Point Light を選択して
and either go to Edit - Duplicate or use
メニューから Edit へ移動してDuplicate を選びます。
command-D on Mac or control-D on PC.
Mac 上では Cmd + D、 PC 上では Ctrl + D
Now we have two lights in the same location
このとき 2 つのライトは同じ位置にあるので、
so again we can use the translate tool
再び位置調整ツールを使用して
and drag the Z axis
Z 軸に沿って
to move it along slightly.
わずかに移動します。
We'll move this one to the centre of the room
さらに部屋の中心部へ移動して
and duplicate once more
もう一度 Duplicate して
and drag this to the end of the room.
今度は部屋の端に移動します。
If you'd like, play around with the settings
さらにカラーやレンジをを調整してライティングを好みに合わせるならば
for colour and range to get a lighting
このときに変更をします。作業が完了したらこれらのライトをドラッグして
that you're more happy with.
このときに変更をします。
When you're finished, drag and drop these lights
作業が完了したらこれらのライトをドラッグして
on to the lights_Baked object
LightsBaked オブジェクトの上にドロップして、
to keep them organised in the hierarchy
すでに現在のHierarchy ビュー上
that we already have.
で整理された階層の中に入れます。
You can then collapse this back up.
この階層は再び展開することが出来ます。
Next we need to change the render settings.
次にレンダリング設定を変更します。
These are found under Edit - Render Settings.
これら設定はEdit メニューの Render Settings のところにあります。
Change them to the values shown here.
これから見せる値に変更します。
First we'll enable fog,
最初にフォグを有効にして
we will give it a purple colour,
紫色に変更します。
we will change the density to 0.04,
さらにDensity は 0.04 に変更して
we will set the linear start to 3,
Linear Start を 3.0 へと変更して
the end to 24
End を 24 へ変更して
and we will set ambient light to black.
Ambient Light を黒色にします。
Next we need to change some of
次に画質設定のいくつかを
the quality settings. These can be found
調整します。
under Edit - Project Settings - Quality.
これはメニューの Edit - Project Settings - Quality で設定できます。
For the purpose of this tutorial project
このチュートリアルプロジェクトにおいては
we recommend choosing Beautiful or Fantastic.
Beautiful または Fantastic を選択することを推奨します。
But if you find that you suffer from lower
しかし、それでパフォーマンスが低下する場合には
performance you can choose Good.
Good を選択したうえで、
And set the number of Pixel Lights
Pixel Light の数を
to a minimum of 6.
6 以上にします。
we will be exporting this as a web player
今後はウェブプレイヤーまたは
or standalone, so remember to set these
スタンドアローンのプラットフォームに対応させるため
as the default under those two platforms.
忘れずにこれらの二つのプラットフォームで Default として
The first column representing web,
ひとつめのカラムがウェブプレイヤーを表し、
and the second represents standalone.
ふたつめがカラムスタンドアローンを表します
Click on the arrow under default
Defaultの下にある矢印をクリックしてを選択して
and choose Beautiful for both of these
両方で Beautiful を選択するか、
or Good depending on your hardware.
または使用するハードウェアによっては Good を選択します。
Next we come to baking the light map.
次にライトの焼き込みを行います。
Baking the light map is a process of saving
ライトの焼き込みとは、全てのライティングをテクスチャに保存することであり、
all of our lighting to a texture.
これらは Light Mapping ウィンドウで作業を行います。
If you don't have your light mapping window
もし Light Mapping ウィンドウをすでに開いてない場合
open already, go to Window - Light Mapping.
メニューから Window - Light Mapping で開きます。
With the light mapping window open click
Light Mapping ウィンドウを開いた状態で
on the Bake tab at the top.
Bake タブをクリックします。
Start by setting the mode to directional light maps.
上部から Mode を Directional Lightmaps に設定します。
For now set the quality to Low.
この時点では Quality を Low に設定して下さい。
we will do a high quality bake later.
高画質の焼き込みは後ほど行います。
Set the number of bounces to 4
Bounces は 4 に設定して
set Bounce Boost to 0.5
Bounce Boost を 0.5 に変更して
leaving Intensity at 1.
Bounce Intensity は 1 のままにして、
Set the Contrast Threshold to 0.05
Contrast Threshold を 0.05 にして、
set Interpolation to 0.25.
Interpolation を 0.25 にして、
Set Interpolation Points to 30,
Interpolation Points を 30 にして、
Ambient Occlusion to 1.
Ambient Occlusion を 1 にして、
Max Distance for the ambient occlusion
Ambient Occlusion の Max Distance を 0.25にして
to 0.25, Contrast to 0
Contrast をゼロにして
and at the bottom set Resolution to 30
最下部では Resolution を 30
texels per world unit
Texels per world unit にして
and set the Padding to 2.
Padding を 2 にします。
Whilst this is a lot of detailed setting
このビデオの下部にあるリンクから
you can see the Light Mapping documentation
Light Mapping ドキュメントへ移動すれば
via the link below this video.
多くの設定の説明が見られます
Now we can bake the scene.
これでシーンの焼き込みを行うことが出来ます。
Click Bake Scene at the bottom.
下部にある Bake Scene をクリックします。
This will take a few minutes.
これは数分かかりますので
You may wish to pause the video now and
このYoutube ビデオはポーズをして、
continue once your bake is finished.
自ら焼き込みが終わるまで待つと良いかもしれません。
Once you've clicked Bake Scene you'll see
Bake Scene をクリックすると
a progress bar saying Exporting
Exporting メッセージとともに進捗バーが表示されて、
and then a further progress bar in the bottom
さらに Unity 画面の右下隅にもうひとつの進捗バーが
right of the Unity interface.
表示されます。
Once your bake is finished you'll see
焼き込みが終わると
an assets progress bar as it imports
Assets 進捗バーにより作成したライトのテクスチャをインポートするうえでの
textures for the light map that it's created.
進捗が表示されます。
Next we need to make a light to dynamically
次にプレイヤーを動的にライティングするライト作成が必要です。
cast shadows. Create a new directional light
これによりプレイヤーのシャドウが描画されます。
game object by going to Create
新規で Directional Light ゲームオブジェクトを作成するために Hierarchy パネル上で
on the hierarchy panel, and choosing
Create をクリックします。
Directional Light. Name the light
さらに Directional Light を選択して
light_main_directional.
ライトの名前を light_main_directional に変更します。
We want to reference this light in code
コードの中でライトを参照して
so that we can fade it when the alarm
アラーム警報が鳴ったときはフェードさせるようにします。
is going off. This way the alarm light won't
これによりアラームライトは邪魔されないような仕組みとするため
be interfered with. To reference it
参照する際にタグ付けを
we're going to use a tag.
インスペクタ上で行います。
From the inspector
タグについては
choose the tag MainLight
MainLights を選択します。
We now want to tweak the settings
ここでライト設定の調整を
for the light slightly.
行います。
We want the game to have quite a dark atmosphere
ゲームは暗い環境にしたいため、
so we will change this light's colour
ライトの色を変更して
to a blue-grey colour.
灰色がかった青にします。
If you want to copy the exact colour we're going to use
もしチュートリアルの色を再現したい場合は
set the colour to 33, 45, 48.
色を (33, 45, 48) にします。
Close the colour picker.
カラー選択を閉じます。
Now we will set the shadows to Soft Shadows.
次にシャドウを Soft Shadows に変更します。
We're going to tweak the shadow settings
シャドウの調整を行って、
slightly so that the bias is 0.01,
Bias が 0.01、
Softness is 4 and the Softness Fade is 0.8.
Softness が 4、そして Softness Fade が 0.8 となるようにします。
The Bias is a setting that represents how
Bias はシャドウが行われはじめる距離を
far from objects the shadow starts.
表します。
Values that are too low will produce artefacts
小さすぎる値だと画像の乱れが生じて、
and values that are too high will mean that
大きすぎる値では
the objects appear to be hovering.
オブジェクトが浮いているように見えます。
The softness is how harsh the lines of the
Softness はシャドウの線がどれだけスムーズであるかであり
shadow are, and the softness fade
Softness Fade は
is a measure of how far from the camera
どれだけカメラから遠くで
soft shadows are drawn.
Soft Shadows が描かれるかを表す距離です。
The last tweak we need to make to the
最後に Light コンポネーント自身の調整が
light component itself is to effect which
必要です。
layers are on it's Culling Mask.
どのレイヤーが Culling Mask 上におくか決めます。
The Culling Mask is a list of layers
Culling Mask は ライトが影響する
the light will effect. We don't need this light
レイヤーの一覧です。ライトは extents レイヤーに
to effect the extents layer
影響させる必要がないため
so we will deselect it from the culling mask.
Culling Mask を非選択にします。
Click on the culling mask drop down
Culling Masks ドロップダウンをクリックして
and deselect Extents by clicking on it.
Extents が非選択となるようにクリックします。
The last change we want to make to this light
最後に行うべきライトへの変更は
is to change it's rotation so that it's
Rotation の変更です。
casting a shadow in a more visually
これによりシャドウが望む方向に伸びるようにします。
pleasing direction. Change the rotation
Rotationの設定を変更して
to 45, 305, 0.
(45, 305, 0) にします。
You will now see these shadows in the scene view.
これによりシーン上でシャドウが表示されます。
Now remember that with a directional light
Directional Light において Position は
the position is irrelevant, only the
まったく影響しないことを覚えてください。
rotation matters. Next we need to make
Rotation だけ意味があります。
a light that will show red when the alarm
次に赤色を発するライトを作成します。
is going off.
これはアラーム警報が鳴ったときに発動します。
This will also be a directional light
これも Directional Light として作成し、
and will share a lot of the same settings
これは、さきほどまで行った Main Light 設定と
that we've just done with the main light.
かなりの部分が同じです。
So we will simply duplicate this to make
このため Alarm Light を
the alarm light.
Duplicate することにします。
Select it and do command-D, or control-D on PC
Alarm Light を選択してCmd + d または PC 上で Ctrol + d を選択するか
or go to Edit - Duplicate.
メニューから Edit - Duplicate を選択します。
We will rename this light_alarm_directional.
名前変更を行ってlight_alarm_directional とします。
Again we're going to need to reference
再びコードを通じてオブジェクトを参照する
this game object through code
必要があります。
so we're going to tag it. Use the tag
このためタグ付けを行います。
drop down menu and choose AlarmLight.
Tag ドロップダウンメニューを使用してAlarmLight を選択します。
We also want to tweak the settings of this light.
設定についても調整を行うことにして
red glow so that the player knows that
今回は主張の強い赤い光として異常事態の発生を
they're in trouble. Let's start with
プレイヤーに告げます。
changing the colour to a dark red.
まずは色を 暗い赤に変更します。
Click on the colour
Color を選択して、
and choose red, then copy our settings.
赤色を選択して、同じ色を再現するには
70, 0, 0.
(70, 0, 0) とします。
Then close the colour picker.
カラー選択を閉じます。
Since the alarm won't be on at the start
アラームはゲームが始まる時に鳴るべきでないため
of the game, set the intensity to 0.
Intensity を 0 にします。
We also want to effect the extents of light.
さらに extents ライトに影響するようにします。
So we need to change our culling mask
このため Culling Mask を再び Everything に変更する
back to Everything.
必要があります。
Under Culling Mask click the drop down
Culling Mask からドロップダウンをクリックして
and choose Everything to reselect the extents.
Everything を選択します。これで extents が再度選択されます。
The last thing we want to do with these lights
最後にやるべきことは ライトマッピングを
is to change their light mapping settings.
変更することです。
We already have a preliminary bake
すでに簡易的なライトマップの
of the light map but we're going to do a
焼き込みは行いましたが、
high quality bake later on.
高画質なライトの焼き込みは後ほど行います。
We don't want these lights to be included
これらのライトは焼き込みの際に含めたくないため
in the bake so we're going to change them
Real Time Only に変更
to Real Time Only.
していきます。
Highlight both the alarm light and the
Alarm light および
main light in the hierarchy
Main Light を Hierarchy 上で選択したうえで
and then set Lightmapping to RealTimeOnly.
Light mapping を Real Time Only に変更します。
And that's it for this assignment.
これで今回のチャプターは終了です。
Move on to the next one to start learning
次のチャプターに進んで、
how to code the alarm systems.
アラームライトをコードから変更する方法を学んでいきます。
Remember to save your scene before moving on.
ここで必ず保存を行うために、
Go to File - Save Scene.
メニューから File - Save Scene を選択して下さい。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)